This might be the most important
nutrient that you can consume on a daily
basis for its widespread benefits,
including cancer. You'll see exactly
what I mean when we dive into the cancer
studies, but I'm curious if you can
guess what it is based on a few
physiological clues that I'll offer.
Clue number one, according to
mechanistic data, something that
promotes cancer progression is
cholesterol. So in fact we can see that
partly evidenced here where three
different human cancer cell lines were
exposed to cholesterol containing
lipoproteins seen here. We have two of
the human cancers and the researchers
measured the aggressiveness or the
migration of these cancer cells when
exposed to the cholesterol containing
lipoprotein. So LDL there on the right
or not the control on the left. The
higher the bars, the worse the cancer
aggression, indicating LDL exposure
increases certain cancer aggression.
Now, there's the first hint. The
nutrient we're going over reduces
cholesterol levels through a number of
mechanisms, including reducing the
absorption. Clue number two, there's a
huge study wherein the researchers show
that bile, so a yellow green fluid that
your liver produces, can turn harmful
and become pro-cancerous. Typically bile
is produced by your liver in a
conjugated form and it helps remove
cholesterol, remove waste products and
help in digestion. However, in your gut
microbiome where billions of bacteria
live can convert depending on the
bacterium conjugated bile to
unconjugated bile. We see that here. The
orange bar is the bacterium that has the
enzyme for converting conjugated to
unconjugated bile. Clearly, there's an
increase relative to the left bacterium
without that enzyme. Okay, but why do we
care? Well, for one, the more
unconjugated bile, as seen here, the
more tumors. Orange is the condition
with more unconjugated bile.
Technically, that's an association, but
the study goes on to show more
definitive proof to implicate
unconjugated bile as carcinogenic. But
we aren't going to dominate this with
bile talk. The second reason we care is
because the second clue for our mystery
molecules function is here. The nutrient
blocks the conversion of conjugated bile
to unconjugated bile keeping it in its
safe form. Specifically, it can bind
bile acid salts and stop them from being
absorbed. But it also encourages the
production of bacteria that don't have
the enzyme expression for this bile
conversion. That enzyme is called bile
salt hydrolace, which is why we saw BSH
under the bars earlier. Okay, two clues.
Let's do one more because it's
fascinating what this nutrient does to
your body. We've been focused so much on
the effects on the gut and it might be
reasonable to say, okay, okay, it might
prevent gut derived cancers like colon
cancer, but can we branch that out and
look at cancers that extend far away
like breast cancer as one example? In
this study, researchers treated breast
cancer cells with a molecule tightly
related to our nutrient of interest and
measured over days the growth of these
cancer cells. Here we see the growth of
the cells. The further up the lines go,
the more cancer cells there are over
time on the horizontal axis. So up is
bad. We're comparing against the control
there, the cancer cells growing
unexposed to the molecule of the study.
Clearly, at all concentrations, there's
at least a slowing of the cancer cell
division. So, the number of cancer
cells. What's especially remarkable is
that at the highest concentrations,
we're seeing a lot of cancer death as we
see the lines dip below the starting
point. So, this molecule in greater
concentrations that is produced by the
nutrient that we're about to unveil is
dealing a serious anti-cancer punch. So,
that's the third clue. This molecule is
produced from our nutrient of interest.
So we have a collection of clues. It
reduces cholesterol. It stops intestinal
conversion of bile acids to
cancerpromoting forms. And it gets
converted to a potent anti-cancer
molecule. Before we get to guessing, I
should note that these three studies,
while telling aren't foolproof. We'd
need more evidence. But I'm giving you
only a sample of the total literature on
the topic as each of these could be
separate investigations in their own
right. There's so much more to say.
Anyway, what do you think the nutrient
is? Let's do multiple choice. A omega-3
fats,
B. Staten drugs, C dietary fiber, or D.
Curcumin. If you choose B, I'd like to
know what you consider a nutritious
meal. I have concerns. Well, they all
have merit, but only one fulfills all
three of these clues, and that's dietary
fiber. Of course, if you got it right,
that's pretty impressive. If you've uh
seen my coverage on butyrate, that third
clue, you had an advantage. But even so,
the other two are not as intuitive. So,
nice work. Okay, we have three studies
and actually one systematic review that
I didn't discuss that indicate that
dietary fiber provides multiple
mechanistic benefits in combating
cancer. But that just isn't good enough
because we should get into more human
data and also getting into how much
fiber is optimal for potential cancer
benefits. I say potential because
mechanistic research is simply not
enough to get a clear realworld idea if
something is actually going to help. We
need more long-term human research. How
about an analysis of over 350,000
people? Bring it on in here. In this
analysis, researchers had data that was
collected from around 500,000 people and
slimmed it down to about 350,000 because
they removed people who already had
cancer or their fiber intake data was
missing. Then they tried to find the
relationship between fiber intake and a
bunch of different type cancer types
from lung cancer to cervical cancer to
kidney, prostate, breast, uterine,
colorctyl, and more. Okay, I'll go ahead
and tell you that the results aren't as
cut and dry as the mechanistic data.
Let's walk through it. When looking at
all the cancers put together, that's 21
different regions of the body. I think
like something like 17 types of cancer,
if I remember correctly, we see that
here. You see that line running down the
middle? That's the baseline risk that
we're comparing against. Technically,
the lowest fiber tier at the top has its
data on that line. It's the lowest
meaning the lowest fiber consumption.
And then as you pan down, fiber intake
increases with the final one trend
indicating the average change as you go
from one quintile upward to the next. If
the squares move to the left, there's
reduced risk of cancer. And the lines
coming out of the squares known as
confidence intervals indicate the
certainty of the data. So the smaller
the better. And if they don't cross the
middle baseline, then that indicates a
statistically identified effect or
relationship in this case. I'm telling
you all this because I'm going to be
throwing some curve balls at you
shortly. But overall, all cancers
combined, there's clearly reduced risk
correlated with fiber consumption. And
the more the better with about a 10%
reduced risk in overall cancer at the
highest intake. We'll get into what that
is soon. Yet, these data are
correlational. So, the researchers also
did a bunch of adjustments to control
for potential confounding factors like
these. We'll return to that. But while
we could close the book on this and just
finish it by saying, "Yay, all right,
fiber fights cancer," that's not
entirely true based on the data. For
example, if we look at uterine cancer,
the results indicate no relationship.
So, no benefit of fiber. The most likely
explanation is that there's insufficient
data because the confidence intervals
that we talked about earlier indicate a
lot of uncertainty. On the other hand,
even cancers with greater certainty like
prostate cancer indicate no
relationship. Yet, breast esophageal and
lung cancers to name a few show a
relationship between fiber intake and
reduced cancer risk. In fact, lung
cancer risk is reduced by over 30% at
the highest fiber intakes. As an
interesting side note, the researchers
point out that the effect is not present
in people who have never smoked. So the
big point here is that there are likely
two factors at play here. One, some of
these cancers we don't have enough data
to say with certainty. Two, some cancers
may not be as positively impacted by
fiber consumption. It may be cancer
specific even if we pull all the cancers
together and see a positive
relationship. However, we can say this.
The relationship between high fiber
intake and all included cancers is
either neutral or positive with none
indicating a harmful relationship. So,
that leaves us with how much fiber is
best. By the way, if you'd like a deeper
analysis on all this, breaking each
cancer down for you along with different
types of fiber, how it affects different
subgroups of people, and more, check out
the full analysis of this video that
you're watching. It's included for the
Physionic Insiders along with a private
podcast, articles every week, an
extensive video library, live sessions
with me, and more. And it's an awesome
community over there. Would love to have
you join. And the link to join is in the
description box. So, remember when we
discussed the lowest to highest fiber
intake? The lowest was less than 10 g or
so per day, and the highest was around
19 g and higher. But that's still too
general because it doesn't detail how
much above 19 g. 19 g is a minimum for
what we just went over. But is 30 g
better than 19 g? Well, sometimes more
is not better. Unfortunately, the large
analysis that we've been leaning on just
doesn't offer those answers.
But fortunately, this analysis does. You
like how I got all depressed like uh we
weren't going to get the answers and
then I came in and saved the day for the
problem that I artificially created the
roller coaster of data. So while this
analysis focused on breast cancer and
yes they also found a relationship with
reduced risk shown here by the way when
I was only a few years old I was already
publishing cancer studies. I was a
genius child. that or that's someone
else with the same last name, whichever
is more believable to you. I know you're
leaning towards the former and I'm
flattered, but uh just know that a lot
of different people have called me an
idiot in the past. So, back to the
point, fiber is linked to reduced breast
cancer. Then, the researchers indicated
a dose response curve on intake here. If
we see the lines go down, that's reduced
risk with the dotted line on either side
indicating the certainty like the
confidence intervals that we discussed
earlier. The horizontal axis is where
the answer lies. It's the fiber dose.
Clearly, going beyond 19 g indicates
further benefit, at least up to 30 g or
so. Then, although the solid black line
continues down, the confidence intervals
widen, indicating greater uncertainty.
Even so, the highest these data go up to
is about 40 grams. So, what to make of
all that? 30 grams seems a safe bet, but
it does seem like more probably won't
have any negative effects in regard to
cancer relationship. So, you might reap
even more reward going higher than 30 g.
Now, one final warning before we package
this all up into a quick summary of
everything. Remember when I mentioned uh
this
yet these data are correlational. So the
researchers also did a bunch of
adjustments to control for potential
confounding factors like these. I'm
bringing that back up because that means
that we typically can't make cause and
effect statements on fiber and cancer.
It's always possible some other
unaccounted for factor is tracking with
fiber that's actually causing these
effects. However, there are more than
just the studies that we've just been
over. There are many, many, many more
studies with all with varying ways of
slicing and dicing the data and in
massive samples of people across
different living situations, uh, health,
ages, and much more. And virtually all
of them come to the same conclusion.
Dietary fiber reduces cancer risk. So,
the evidence beyond the ones that we've
covered is very strong. That leaves us
with a few main points to take home with
us. One, dietary fiber has multiple
discovered mechanisms by which it
reduces cancer risk, but also directly
stresses cancer cells. Two, dietary
fiber reduces overall cancer risk. But
the evidence is mixed on different types
of cancer. Some show a positive
relationship and some show a neutral for
varying reasons. But the overall point
is that there's robust evidence
indicating dietary fiber is good for you
if you care about reducing your cancer
risk.
Three, the optimal amount of dietary
fiber is at least 30 gram of fiber on
average with more being potentially
better. If you are consuming less than
that, you're likely at increased
relative cancer risk. Now, you know how
I mentioned there's this molecule that
gets produced from fiber and it kills
cancer cells? In fact, there's a tricky
but mindblowingly cool way that it
overwhelms cancer, but only in certain
contexts. I covered that in this next
video right here. Check it out. Thanks
for tuning in.